broadcasting the information the
mainstream media won't touch this is the
Ritchie Allen show in association with
David Icke calm our next guest is a hero
it's a big word and it's award I don't
use very often in fact I very rarely use
it he really is a hero he spent two
years in prison as you will know by now
from februari 2013 to februari last year
for basically blowing the whistle on
torture and on CIA torture CIA rendition
and the water boarding techniques used
to interrogate al Qaeda prisoners as I
take some goats known what you know no
Marty inevitable outcome of it is when
you do blow the whistle and you do you
know expose these things you know you're
going to be targeted as he was he's
known also as a writer for Huffington
Post he writes for them he's been a
terrorism analyst for ABC news as well
as much more besides he's at his resume
would keep us here all night long so
let's just welcome to the program he's
in Pennsylvania terrific to welcome for
the first time to this show John
Kiriakou John welcome to the show how
are you thank you so much I'm very well
thanks thank you very much for having me
and you know I meant it when I said hero
John because it's not easy to do what
you did you know people say all the time
I wish more people came out from law
enforcement from the military to expose
these things John the fact of the matter
is people know when you do that you're
gonna be in trouble you know sometimes I
wake up and I think I was just an idiot
but I don't think you're an idiot but I
suppose when you're in prison for two
years you must have had your moments
John I I did you know when you when you
first arrived in prison you're you're in
shock and you just can't believe that
this has happened just a few years
earlier i was you know briefing the
President and and meeting with with
kings and prime ministers and then here
i find myself you know sitting at the
Aryan table for dinner imagine that John
Dee Aryan table I mean throw so many
pictures into my into into my mind
straight away of all those TV shows
Prison Break and stuff like us but
they're mostly dark times I mean as yet
quite rightly said you you've been a top
CIA and
Liston case officer you briefed the
president you briefed top officials the
Joint Chiefs you were you know you were
writing amongst these people next thing
you find yourself in prison for doing
the right thing which is that your
government and your organization was
breaking the law they were breaking the
line you know what was really clear to
me was was that this was obviously an
illegal act we have we we have had
something in the United States called
the the federal torture act since 1947
and it specifically defines torture and
specifically outlaws it besides the
federal torture Act we are not just the
signatories or not just i should say
signatories to the UN Convention Against
Torture we were the authors of the UN
Convention Against Torture and so I just
couldn't understand how anybody could
possibly believe that this torture
program that we had conceived of was
somehow legal tell me when you first I
mean look first of all let's be honest a
lot of our listeners will know this but
we don't assume knowledge and their
program is a crossover prog John between
what you'd call mainstream commercial
radio and more alternative independent
radio so the right people listen to this
they were no your course there were no
your your name and who you are but not
the details so when did you come to
understand that people were being
tortured by US military personnel well I
had been the the chief of the CIA's
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
after September 11th and in that
position I led a series of raids in late
march two thousand two that resulted in
the capture of Abu Zubaydah whom we
believed at the time was the number
three in al-qaeda and so when I finished
that tour in the early summer of two
thousand two and I went back to CIA
headquarters I happened to be in the
cafeteria one day and a senior officer
from the CIA's Counterterrorism Center
called ctc approached me in the
cafeteria and said oh I'm glad I ran
into you I wanted to ask you if you were
interested in being certified in the use
of enhanced interrogation techniques
well I had never heard of this term
before and I said well
that supposed to mean so very excitedly
he said we're going to start getting
rough with these guys and I said well
what is rough mean so he outlined to me
these ten different torture techniques
that the CIA was was intending to
implement in fact they did implement
them about three months later and I said
that that sounds like a torture program
I don't think I want to be involved but
you know what I said let me think about
it for an hour and I went up to the
CIA's executive floor the seventh floor
and I I went to see a very senior CIA
officer for whom I had worked in the
Middle East about a decade earlier and I
I told him about the conversation I had
had in the cafeteria and I said what do
you think about this and he said first
let's call it what it is it's torture
they can use whatever euphemism they
want but it's still torture and tortures
a slippery slope and you know how your
coworkers are you know somebody's going
to go overboard and they're gonna kill a
prisoner and when that happens there's
going to be a congressional
investigation and then there's going to
be a criminal investigation and
somebody's gonna go to prison do you
want to go to prison and I said no I
don't want to go to prison as it as it
turned out I was the only one who only
one who went to prison yet but I said no
no I don't want to go to prison and I
went back downstairs to the
Counterterrorism Center and I said this
is a torture program and I don't want to
have anything to do with it and that was
in that was in the middle of may 2002
and then we know now from the CIA's
torture report that the agency began
torturing Abu Zubaydah on august first
of that year and he was waterboarded a
lot of times John wasn't he he was
waterboarded 83 times which you know I
tell I tell college groups to whom I
speak on a regular basis I tell them all
the same story in 1968 in January the
Washington Post ran a front-page
photograph of an American soldier
waterboarding and North Vietnamese
prisoner and the day that photograph
appeared the secretary of defense robert
mcnamara ordered an investigation the
soldier was arrested he was charged with
torture and he was convicted and
imprisoned well the law didn't change
since nineteen sixty eight so why was
waterboarding torture and illegal in
1968 but not in 2002 or in 2015 why did
it take yet another law the McCain fine
Stein amendment to formally officially
finally ban torture torture torture has
always been illegal you I mean I imagine
I've spoken to X servicemen on this
program before ex military servicemen
from the US I'm from Britain now
typically the ones who come on they're
very disillusioned the soldiers they
talk about you know realizing when they
were in Iraq that they weren't really
there for the reasons they were told
they were want to be here and the
horrors of realizing that they were
basically an occupying force in a
country where they were you know going
through villages of you know extremely
poor people and all these horror stories
you get into the CIA John obviously cuz
you're bright you know there's no doubt
about that and you want to be you know
you want to do right by your country and
you want to protect your country from
from from foreign enemies domestic
enemies as well and here you are
learning that this country that you
thought was so virtuous and understood
for the right thing and was so good was
capable of stealing this and I suppose
around about this time as well we learn
about well no it was a couple years
later we learned about Abu Ghraib and
all the things that went on there and
Basra in order what does that do John
what does that do to a guy like you I go
who's well-intentioned in terms of why
you got into the agency yeah I have to
agree with you and with your guess I I
became terribly disillusioned my my
family emigrated to the United States
from Greece in 1931 all four of my
grandparents left the island of Rhodes
in 1931 and landed on Ellis Island and
to hear my paternal grandfather tell it
Franklin Roosevelt was personally
waiting for him in New York Harbor to
offer him a job and freedom and
citizenship in the American dream and so
my grandparents and parents always
instilled in us a sense that
that we needed to repay the country for
the kindness that it showed us and
allowing us to emigrate and so public
service was always very important in my
family so I i went into the CIA thinking
that not only am i going to serve my
country i'm gonna get to see the world
too and i had a facility for foreign
languages i thought well this is great
though they'll pay for a PhD program i
can use my foreign languages I'll see
the world I'll meet important people
this is really going to be a great
career and in the beginning it was and
it was because two presidents George HW
Bush and Bill Clinton actually had
respect for international human rights
the CIA famously went through what they
called a cull where they were they fired
about a third of their recruited sources
because those sources had some sort of
Human Rights problem in their background
and I remember by the mid-1990s saying
well this is great this is this is what
an honorable intelligence service should
be like we should be collecting
intelligence and recruiting spies to
steal secrets but at the same time we
need to be respecting human rights and
that was something really to be proud of
but boy everything changed on September
11th and I remember the first inkling
that things were really going wrong was
when I was in Pakistan and we had it was
the night that we had captured up as a
beta but we had caught many dozens of
other al Qaeda fighters and can I just
interject there weren't a lot of these
fighters that were being picked up
weren't they being handed over boy
people for bounties and a lot of them
ended up in Guantanamo Bay and elsewhere
and they really weren't guilty of
anything oh I would say probably eighty
percent of them were just completely
innocent of any crime and listen here's
what was happening how could not you
know but I'm not speaking about you
specifically but how could military
officers aren't platoon leaders and
commanders how could it be so stupid
John when to be taking people into
custody based on fossil says this guy
over here is you know and you know that
well the voiceless got nothing he can't
even afford to boy and you know the crop
to plant for this for you know for next
season's corn or whatever so course
voiceless want to say he's grandmother's
in al-qaeda sure how did those army guys
those Marines how did they fall for that
this was going on this was my first
sustained exposure to the US military
wrong you know I i would i would brief
you know high-ranking officers every
once in a while but this is the first
time that I actually had to live and
work with them and I found frankly that
most of them were ill-equipped
ill-informed in many cases not very
bright and they just made this decision
early on that they're going to send
everybody literally everybody to
Guantanamo and sort it out later and
Guantanamo was supposed to be this
temporary holding site where we were
going to hold people long enough to
figure out in what district in the
United States they should be tried but
what was happening was like you say if
Mohammed Oh is faisals some money and
facial doesn't want to repay the money
he just goes to the local us you know
sergeant that village and says oh this
guy Mohammed is al Qaeda and then
Mohammed goes to Guantanamo and fiesel
doesn't have to pay the loan back yeah
and we we saw this all the time or if
maybe you wanted to marry my sister and
I didn't like you i went to the
Americans and said you're al-qaeda and
then you end up in Guantanamo for the
next 14 years so that happened a lot but
either the either the US military was
was unwilling or too stupid frankly to
do anything about it and then when you
have a president and vice president like
George W Bush and Dick Cheney setting
the tone for this kind of policy the
situation was almost hopeless for
anybody finding themselves in Guantanamo
24 minutes past the year terrific to
have John Kiriakou on the line twist it
really is takes courage to do what east
on top CIA analyst briefed the well he
briefed to top man he briefed the
President and others like him couple of
people disagree with John agreeing with
him on everything except to Bill Clinton
saying and we don't like Clinton some of
her listener
saying he certainly he certainly was no
champion of human rights and asked asked
the Rwandans about his failure to deal
with genocide air I could have said that
but I don't want to be interrupting you
every couple of minutes John I'm an
arrogant I'm an argumentative Irishman
I'd like to have argument so I'm not
gonna be argument over every single
comment you made I'm not going to do
that for them yeah I wouldn't be any
found or obvious Wi-Fi user listen I'm
going to get this one out of the way
you're a very smart man again I'm not
patronizing you've done your homework so
you know the sort of show this is is and
I've got serious problems with the
official version of september's 11th I
want to get this one out of the way what
do you think um yeah I think there are
some problems with the official version
of september's Evans I'm not what you
might call a 911 truther I don't believe
that there was a controlled explosion or
that Jews did it or the trilateral
commission but you know there are 28
redacted pages redacted from the 911
Commission report that uh that the
American public simply are not allowed
to see I don't know what's in those 28
pages but I can speculate yeah and I
think I believe that those 28 pages
contain documentary evidence of the
official involvement in the 911 attacks
of the Saudi government I don't trust
the Saudis I don't like the Saudis the
Saudis are not reliable allies the
Saudis are monsters when it comes to
human rights horrible aren't I deserve
let's be honest yeah and ironically they
chair the UN Human Rights Commission
right now which is just insane to me Oh
David Cameron should be ridden out of
town on a rail for his part of that I
wife the hell is going on this isn't
space but John Kerry's know better you
know I I wrote a piece of that ran in oh
it's a syndication service here in the
United States called other words org it
runs in 220 small-town newspapers around
the country and I wrote about how the
Saudis were assuming control of this UN
Human Rights Committee and I said it was
absolutely disgraceful for the following
reasons and I listed four or five or six
different reasons and a reporter picked
up the story and wrote a story about it
and asked John Kerry my former boss for
a comment and carry all carry would say
was that he had supreme confidence in
the ability of the Saudis to run the
Human Rights Committee imagine though
like what kind of what kind of hypocrisy
is that it what kind of hypocrisy is it
when an American State Department
officer has to go to a host government
and beat them about the face and head
because of their human rights record
while in the very next room an American
CIA officer is asking that same
government to house a secret prison
where we're going to render somebody and
torture him mercilessly for the next 18
months it's the apocrypha and it's
unacceptable absolutely right 27 minutes
past year I am going to leave 911 I just
want to mention this ah he came up in
commercial radio John I didn't study
journalism in school I laterally went to
uni and studied am university and
studied history in English then went on
to do a postgraduate degree in
television and radio and I broadcast
live on sep tember eleven's I took over
me and my presenter took over the
afternoon schedule of wor feminine and
very very successful commercial radio
station we took all the afternoon jocks
off the air because what was going on at
nine a.m. in new york city and we of
course them we did what we were told we
took the Associated Press wires we took
Reuters and we within days we were
saying that bin Laden did it in and
these these hijackers didn't all of that
it was a couple years later that I began
to have reservations about it I didn't
have any background in conspiracy
theories had no interest in conspiracy
theories but reading psalmist keynes
book two books are read one written by
david icke and one written by thomas
kean who was a commission chairman where
he basically said they gave us five
million dollars to investigate the worst
terrorist atrocity in America we spent
much more morning investigating whether
bill clinton received oral sex from an
intern right he said it was set up to
fail keen I've come to the conclusion i
admire i believe you're honest I believe
you are given your calling as you see it
I have no idea how those towers came
down I really don't and I get really
pissed off with some
truthers killing one another over
whether it was demolitions or whether it
was the planes or whatever what I've
come to believe is and this kills me it
kills me to live in a world where I
believe this I've come to believe that
agents of the US government may be
working with agents to the British
government may be working with the
Saudis maybe um to further an agenda Oh
either brought the building say in one
way or another or equally as badly John
they allowed somebody else to another
was [__] blind oi twist and and
that's what I believe the first week a
matter what I believe because my
listeners know it kills me to live in a
world like that then people are capable
of doing that what hey think what
disagree with you especially with the
last thing that you said frankly I I
don't know what the truth is I can tell
you what Abu Zubaydah told me um he told
me that he didn't want to attack the
United States on 911 that he wanted to
attack Israel he said all he wanted to
do was to kill Jews he didn't want to
attack the United States but that he had
been overruled and he was the one who
told us that Khalid Sheikh Mohammed was
was the mastermind we knew that that the
mastermind was somebody named more
thought but we didn't know who this MOOC
thought was until Abu Zubaydah told
Alice oof on an FBI agent who was
debriefing him at the time so that was
the only indication that we had now with
that said I think a strong argument for
conspiracy can be made because what has
happened in the post 9-11 era is that we
have transitioned to a full-time wartime
economy and after all these years mind
you September 11th is nearly 15 years
ago we have been in a wartime footing
without that massive federal spending on
on armaments and on a very large
military much larger than we need to
defend ourselves certainly the economy
would go into depression we just
couldn't maintain this level of spending
so you know what I I'm not going to
disagree with you I think there could be
something to it and I think that
probably we're never going to know the
truth you know I get them I always get
tweets from listeners where
we go out on several platforms and our
audience is very big I don't say that to
brag but it is big and I get I'll get
these emails in these tweets oh he won't
tell the truth and he's he's working for
the system and what some people don't
understand is they're just not prepared
to understand that you know there are so
many different points of view on this
and we're talking to John Kiriakou who's
worked for the CIA he worked for them
for the right reasons he got into his
job as he quickly explained haven't been
he's family hasn't being immigrants
second third generation and a
greek-american who wanted to invest
something back into as a country that
are taking care of his family looking
after looking after taking care of the
country protecting it against enemies
foreign and domestic and all of that I
think John's been incredibly honest to
say that he's not sure or you know he
wouldn't rule it out or it's not beyond
the bounds of possibility because he
means that I meet people all the time
listen we have families who think it's
crazy it's our 911 was a self-inflicted
wound we have to get over this calling
people shields and protectors just
because they're not sure about it raises
Christ I'm delighted that he's saying
he's not sure about it that's a start
for me you know like I had a really
great friend a former very senior CIA
officer by the name of Ray McGovern yeah
we love raise a regular on this program
ray Oh ray is just a grilling on ya like
a brother to me and you know ray ray is
his thinking on this issue is far closer
to yours than it bet it is to mine ray
is convinced that that it was a
conspiracy and that if bin Laden was was
involved that that bin Laden was used as
a as a stooge yeah he does to be honest
now as long as I've I mean I've known
ray about two years which isn't long and
the grand scheme of things but when he's
been on he's been commenting on on Syria
and Crimea Ukraine and Russia obviously
as you well know and that's lovely but
I've never kind of dog I'm very polite
about it John I don't want to scare guys
like you off I'll tell you why and this
might sound very patronizing what I'm
trying to do here and other producers
who believe some things that are
considered extreme I don't want to use
go I'm not trying to use you
all I want our listeners to hear a guy
like you had the courage to talk about
torture and because you saw what you saw
you're now looking at other things
you're you're considering the
possibilities because ultimately all I
want people to do right exactly it's
considered sex exactly and I love it you
know come it can we talk about am Syria
is it fair to say and you know your
great friend and an air friend Ray
McGovern certainly agrees with this that
tomorrow or wednesday is notes tomorrow
is the meteor hilarious jhanda calling
it the fifth anniversary of the uprising
now I'm not going to say for a minute is
that Bashar al-assad and his government
didn't have opposition who wanted Syria
to be more democratic I have no doubt
people like that lived there it was an
autocracy we know that an authoritarian
am country we could say regime I don't
like saying regime but isn't it fair to
say that all the evidence now points to
our intelligence agencies here in in
London mi6 the CIA the NSA and other
dark actors basically handed all the
money in all the weapons that he could
find to so-called moderate opposition
groups in Syria as far back as 2008 2009
to unleash the absolute mayhem that
we've seen there now and I'm not for a
minute saying that Assad is an angel I'm
not what I'm saying that again we've
been caught out again red-handed and I
say we Britain the United States and
others in destabilizing the country's
out might have been a glowing beacon of
democracy in the region at all what was
was was a much better place before we
decided to stick our all in what are
your thoughts yeah I agree with that and
and this is really yet another example
of this misguided and in many cases
illegal neoconservative foreign policy
that we have and it spans
administration's it's not just George W
Bush Barack Obama is just as as
complicit in this as George W Bush was
um yeah I think you're right I think the
idea was that that we would arm as many
people in Syria as we possibly could
because they they were ostensibly
opposed to Bashar al-assad
and may work with us against Isis wants
Isis was created of course we're the
reason Isis was created in the first
place and then of course all hell broke
loose the thing is is let me let me give
you an example when we were planning the
Iraq war there were very clearly drawn
battle lines within the US government
and of course this was all behind closed
doors but the office of the vice
president the office of the secretary of
defense and the National Security
Council were gung-ho to invade Iraq the
CIA the State Department and the Joint
Chiefs of Staff were saying this is a
mistake we need to focus on al-qaeda we
need to find bin Laden we shouldn't
invade Iraq um and I remember an NSC a
national security council senior
director said hanging at a secure video
teleconference that as soon as we cross
the border into Iraq the Iraqi people
are going to throw flowers at us that's
what he said and you get that same
neocon attitude when you talk to these
people about Syria that well what the
Syrians need is a democracy along with a
moderate you know sunni-led body politic
well wait a minute there's no history of
democracy anywhere in the Levant
especially a us-style democracy and who
are we to impose our form of government
on anybody else in the meantime we're
art we're arming practically all sides
which keep our or munitions factories
running at full blast when why is it
really happening John well we I'm going
to be talking tomorrow about the Des
Moines current crisis and the fact that
we know that angle a miracle in Germany
got a right kick in the backside boy the
electorate over the weekend I the
midterm I suppose we could call in the
midterm elections but the local
elections and the regional elections lot
of right-wing candidates have done well
because she basically opened the
floodgates to as the migrants what about
those like David Icke say for example
and and others who say that that the
crisis the mass movement of people
across Europe is an intended consequence
of the madness of destroying Libya and
Syria and that ultimately what that is
about is it's ultimately about dividing
and conquering it's about controlling us
I think that's exactly what it is I
think that's exactly what it is because
we went when we have this kind of
aggressive foreign policy we want
everybody else to be weak because that's
how we control them we want Libya in
chaos Assyria in chaos and Afghanistan
and chaos now our allies are going to
disagree with us behind closed doors
which is exactly why you don't see the
Israelis in any way supporting what's
happening in in Syria because as far as
the Israelis are concerned the devil
they know is better than the devil they
don't and they know that Bashar al-assad
is no threat to them well to the United
States and to the UK and to others we
like to stir the pot we like to keep
everybody off balance now that tends to
fail pretty spectacularly look what
happened in Iraq Saddam Hussein was the
only bulwark against Iran he was the
only thing that kept Iran from meddling
in the in the small Gulf states for
example or posing a greater threat to to
Lebanon now when you say meddling now
using you know doing basically what we
do sending arms because yeah because the
Iranians historically they don't really
attack anybody so they don't know no
actually the Iranians don't the Iranians
never have attacked anybody I mean even
in the Iranian rock war as bad as Saddam
Hussein was the Iranians didn't attack
it was Saddam who attacked them that's
right with weapons delivered by among
states why the United States yeah yeah
so of course we knew all along what
Saddam didn't didn't have because what
he had we gave it to it was pretty clear
to uh to well most all of us in the CIA
that there were no weapon
mass destruction and we told the White
House that repeatedly that there were no
weapons of mass destruction we knew that
that the nuclear program had had been
dismantled in the late 1980s we knew
that the well biological weapons you can
make in your kitchen in your home so
there's just no way to know besides they
had no delivery system but chemical
weapons which is where everybody was
wrapped around the axle there was just
simply no evidence that the Iraqis had
chemical weapons they had had them in in
earlier years but they had destroyed
them thanks to the UN weapons
inspections all throughout the 1990s
yeah Oh John I want to do a quick time
check I'm so glad you're on the program
20 minutes to the top of the air I i I'm
very self-critical and I didn't want to
sound patronizing when I was explaining
you know why it's so important to bring
ray mcgovern on you another Jean and
because John there are three types of
people there are people who believe in a
very very very sinister conspiracy which
is ultimately about you know reducing
the population and doing other very
terrible things I'll be honest I'm in
that group then there's a group of
people then who understands that and
most of our political leaders elected
leaders officials and military men and
women whom we see on TV are telling
noise and they those people then
disagree about the reasons that they're
doing it it's lighter about oil or it's
about money but then there is the
majority of people and the majority of
people who go blissfully living their
lives watching the sports and watching
the the the reality television shows I
don't understand that something is very
very very wrong and I want to bridge the
gap between us and and then I look where
one program but that's kind of exactly
what we and what we were set up for and
yeah and you know and whatever guys like
you we wouldn't have a chance whatever
people like you were on the other side
of the fence working for governments but
saw something was terribly wrong at the
courage to do something Adele didn't boy
the way anybody who wants to see what
other people are tweeting it's all one
word Richie Allen show intuitive press
enter you see what other people are
tweeting Alex was on to say Richie he
was a CIA
he dealt with actionable intelligence
which is much less discriminating then
circumstantial says says alex alex is
not a fan I don't think that's okay yeah
we are we have a democracy kids I I know
how unpopular I am among some circles
and that's fine I accept it I have a
thick skin yeah fair enough you've got
em you got youngster in the background
as well haven't you I can a youngster
backward no it's good it's lovely 17
minutes to Z the the top of the arrow
John kyriacou is our guest it's great to
have him on thanks for the tweets out
Richie Island show on Twitter Richie
Richie an encoded UK we've got John for
another fiver or six minutes so so Putin
said today that Russia is going to draw
down just a smallish force that it has
in Syria we understand it's 30 planes
and it's been a you know a force a
battalion of sorts minding or looking
after those planes and obviously then
the advisors that would be there at
voice and the Syrian government what's
that all about is that to show that
Russia really wants to you know push
forward with the peace process or is it
more gamesmanship it's Putin saying
because at the moment Interpol are
saying well there are thousands of
al-qaeda in Europe already there just
waiting for the opportunity to kill us
all it's potent you're saying we'll hang
on a second we've been we've been
seriously upset in these guys over the
last few months we've killed thousands
of them there's not many left and so
that's kind of one-upmanship or
gamesmanship or is Putin do you think
really determined to get behind a peace
process John you know I honestly believe
and maybe this is maybe this sounds
naive but I I think we ought to take
Putin at face value here I think that he
saw Russian involvement in Syria as as
as a limited prospect in the very
beginning I think the Russians had a far
better defined mission and goal in Syria
certainly than the United States has
where we just you know send people and
forget to bring them home um but I think
that I
think that he's got a plan this is part
of the plan and he's ready to at least
in part go home so I think that what
what we see here is what we get we ought
to take him at his word he's got
problems with Ukraine of course and
that's another you look at Victoria
Nuland the wife of Bob keg and you look
at what they've done in Ukraine there oh
yes I mean this is it's shocking isn't
it I mean they took out I'm Yanukovych
we have poroshenko there I I would use
it I you know I shouldn't probably
should be more professional but ever use
the word like pulpit we have natalie's
Aresco there a Chicago born woman yes
she is of Ukrainian descent but she's
running the she's managing the purse
strings now for Ukraine it's a good boy
any other name so Russia's surrounded or
I could be argued it surrounded with
what's happening in Turkey and Turkey is
very unstable at the moment John he's
guarded bees rush has got to be worried
as a network and this did this brings us
tend to the ideas out there are those
pushing us towards a global conflict
that involves rocha possibly China and
against Britain the United States Israel
the Saudis and others now I want to
believe that that it won't happen that's
what I want to believe but I can't help
but believe that there are those driving
us towards what do you think yeah again
I gonna have to agree with you one of
the things that that American success of
American governments and certainly
American people fail to understand is
that Putin and really most Russians I
think feel and circled by the United
States and its allies they see every
time a NATO adds a new member country
they see that as a threat to their
security as well they should and so I
think that we just fail to understand
their concerns and so when they do
something that's clearly in their own
military interests we see that as a
provocation and we see that as a threat
um I don't think it's a threat I think
it's survived
oh I don't see a global conflict not
because of anything that the United
States does certainly but I think the
Chinese are so cautious and so averse
really to the use of force and I worked
with the Chinese in the United Nations
for many years they really don't like
the use of force I just don't see a
conflagration put it that way I I hope
you're right do you agree with me so
we're back to the neo-cons again oh that
there are those who would who would push
us if not to bring people given the
chance for example given the opportunity
there are those who would em unleash
that yeah I think I think Victoria
Nuland is a dangerous force in the
region and certainly Robert Kaiba Kagan
is even more dangerous uh you know they
there there are organizations think
tanks and places in Washington that
won't even allow them to darken the
hallways and how in the world their
commanding leadership positions in
American foreign policy is just
something that we should all be ashamed
of if not sauna wage on Saudi haven't
these people they've just not gone away
to Alexa bolton and and Wolfowitz and we
mentioned keg and the authors of the
project for a new American Century d0
these people who believe that to
maintain America's hegemony it's got to
be involved in multiple series of wars I
mean when you think about and what was
it Wesley Clark ooh and eavesdropped and
heard things he shouldn't have heard
about the plans for countries like Syria
and Libya and stuff like that
psychopaths they might be but their
plans of coming to come to fruition
haven't do well you they have and it's
been very incremental and in it when
it's incremental like that it's easy to
miss and I think that's exactly what has
happened I mean it seems to me like the
neoconservatives have had their eyes on
Ukraine for years many years maybe
decades and and they finally got the
kind of as you I think appropriately put
it a puppet regime in power right now
you know what listening to you I know
you will have friends some who might
still be in service and summer warrants
what did he may give you John I think
and I don't mean in terms of you going
to prison for doing the right thing
I think most of them would grudgingly
admire you for doing the right thing
torture is wrong and it's a marvelous
thing you did I'll never forget that as
long as the majority's Indian programs
like this you know the easy thing to do
is to turn a blind eye to it you are the
courage not that makes you a great guy
in my opinion no it really does John it
can't be said enough times so you look
at him you look at them people who
served with you people who are still
there what do you think they make of you
talkin now in terms like you have been
about Ukraine and stuff like that what
would they make if what was your opinion
see actually still have a lot of friends
at the CIA um still active duty CIA in
fact um 50 one of them have signed a
letter to the president asking him to
pardon me um so I do hear from them and
they they say that I have overreacted
because of what has happened to me over
the last four years and that I find
fault in too much as it relates to
American policy but I tell them and
listen I'm a lifelong Liberal Democrat
we use the word progressive now but a
lifelong Democrat and they hate it when
I tell them look you know Ronald Reagan
was right government is the problem it's
not the solution to the problem and when
we have a government that wants to have
its hands in everything whether its
expansionist military policy or
expansionist foreign policy or taking
away our civil liberties and carrying
out warrantless wiretaps or cracking
into our iphones that is a problem and I
had a problem yeah he government has
become the problem not the solution John
we had a story today just before we go
it might sound like something small but
it's big you know in Liverpool obviously
a great city of great historical cities
marvelous City he gave us the Beatles
and a couple of terrible soccer teams we
won't get into that I mean I'm in
Manchester's when I'm boys bought em a
couple of women today were fined and
given community service in a quarter
niverville because they refused refused
to obey a zoning order which made it
illegal to give food to the homeless
people
John we're in serious trouble here oh
you see we have the same we have the
same new kinds of laws it's now illegal
in Seattle to provide food to homeless
people and so I hope I this is a very
very new law I hope that people you know
walk into McDonald's or wendy's or
Kentucky Fried Chicken and buy food just
for the homeless yeah they can they can
flout this law and challenge it on the
streets it was disobedience john howard
zinn was right I keep we keep bringing
him up you know you cannot obey
tyrannical laws like that you didn't
obey a tyrannical law it's absolutely
outrageous is that you wouldn't be
pardoned and I'm sick in that some
former and current CIA people said that
you overreacted how could you overreact
to being sentenced to two years in jail
for doing the right thing and telling
people that your government is you know
is committing heinous crimes I think
you're absolutely brilliant a John and
listen there I'd love to have you back
on again in the future to talk about and
you know not so much about your own
story but when when you've got things to
say I know you're right for aura as well
and I probably should have mentioned
that and/or in our TV you find them John
on there but anything that's happening
geopolitically that you're very
interested in yeah you can always come
back on here and I'm a child it's a
really enjoyed having you on thank you
so much pleasures all mine thanks for
inviting me look after yourself John
thanks boyfriend John Kiriakou on the
line to estare from his home in
Pennsylvania
[Music]